<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>Londons miserie, the countryes crueltie with Gods mercie. Explained by remarkeable obseruations of each of them, during this last visitation. VVritten by Richard Milton.</title>
            <author>Milton, Richard.</author>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <edition>
               <date>1625</date>
            </edition>
         </editionStmt>
         <extent>Approx. 64 KB of XML-encoded text transcribed from 21 1-bit group-IV TIFF page images.</extent>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Text Creation Partnership,</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Ann Arbor, MI ; Oxford (UK) :</pubPlace>
            <date when="2011-12">2011-12 (EEBO-TCP Phase 2).</date>
            <idno type="DLPS">A07556</idno>
            <idno type="STC">STC 17939</idno>
            <idno type="STC">ESTC S112778</idno>
            <idno type="EEBO-CITATION">99848022</idno>
            <idno type="PROQUEST">99848022</idno>
            <idno type="VID">13094</idno>
            <availability>
               <p>To the extent possible under law, the Text Creation Partnership has waived all copyright and related or neighboring rights to this keyboarded and encoded edition of the work described above, according to the terms of the CC0 1.0 Public Domain Dedication (http://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/). This waiver does not extend to any page images or other supplementary files associated with this work, which may be protected by copyright or other license restrictions. Please go to https://www.textcreationpartnership.org/ for more information about the project.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <seriesStmt>
            <title>Early English books online.</title>
         </seriesStmt>
         <notesStmt>
            <note>(EEBO-TCP ; phase 2, no. A07556)</note>
            <note>Transcribed from: (Early English Books Online ; image set 13094)</note>
            <note>Images scanned from microfilm: (Early English books, 1475-1640 ; 1635:07)</note>
         </notesStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblFull>
               <titleStmt>
                  <title>Londons miserie, the countryes crueltie with Gods mercie. Explained by remarkeable obseruations of each of them, during this last visitation. VVritten by Richard Milton.</title>
                  <author>Milton, Richard.</author>
               </titleStmt>
               <extent>[4], 36 p.   </extent>
               <publicationStmt>
                  <publisher>Printed by Nicholas Okes,</publisher>
                  <pubPlace>London :</pubPlace>
                  <date>1625.</date>
               </publicationStmt>
               <notesStmt>
                  <note>In verse.</note>
                  <note>Reproduction of the original in the British Library.</note>
               </notesStmt>
            </biblFull>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Created by converting TCP files to TEI P5 using tcp2tei.xsl,
      TEI @ Oxford.
      </p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>EEBO-TCP is a partnership between the Universities of Michigan and Oxford and the publisher ProQuest to create accurately transcribed and encoded texts based on the image sets published by ProQuest via their Early English Books Online (EEBO) database (http://eebo.chadwyck.com). The general aim of EEBO-TCP is to encode one copy (usually the first edition) of every monographic English-language title published between 1473 and 1700 available in EEBO.</p>
            <p>EEBO-TCP aimed to produce large quantities of textual data within the usual project restraints of time and funding, and therefore chose to create diplomatic transcriptions (as opposed to critical editions) with light-touch, mainly structural encoding based on the Text Encoding Initiative (http://www.tei-c.org).</p>
            <p>The EEBO-TCP project was divided into two phases. The 25,368 texts created during Phase 1 of the project (2000-2009), initially available only to institutions that contributed to their creation, were released into the public domain on 1 January 2015. The approximately 40,000 texts produced during Phase 2 (2009- ), of which 34,963 had been released as of 2020, originally similarly restricted, were similarly freed from all restrictions on 1 August 2020. As of that date anyone is free to take and use these texts for any purpose (modify them, annotate them, distribute them, etc.). But we do respectfully request that due credit and attribution be given to their original source.</p>
            <p>Users should be aware of the process of creating the TCP texts, and therefore of any assumptions that can be made about the data.</p>
            <p>Text selection was based on the New Cambridge Bibliography of English Literature (NCBEL). If an author (or for an anonymous work, the title) appears in NCBEL, then their works are eligible for inclusion. Selection was intended to range over a wide variety of subject areas, to reflect the true nature of the print record of the period. In general, first editions of a works in English were prioritized, although there are a number of works in other languages, notably Latin and Welsh, included and sometimes a second or later edition of a work was chosen if there was a compelling reason to do so.</p>
            <p>Image sets were sent to external keying companies for transcription and basic encoding. Quality assurance was then carried out by editorial teams in Oxford and Michigan. 5% (or 5 pages, whichever is the greater) of each text was proofread for accuracy and those which did not meet QA standards were returned to the keyers to be redone. After proofreading, the encoding was enhanced and/or corrected and characters marked as illegible were corrected where possible up to a limit of 100 instances per text. Any remaining illegibles were encoded as &lt;gap&gt;s. Understanding these processes should make clear that, while the overall quality of TCP data is very good, some errors will remain and some readable characters will be marked as illegible. Users should bear in mind that in all likelihood such instances will never have been looked at by a TCP editor.</p>
            <p>The texts were encoded and linked to page images in accordance with level 4 of the TEI in Libraries guidelines.</p>
            <p>Copies of the texts have been issued variously as SGML (TCP schema; ASCII text with mnemonic sdata character entities); displayable XML (TCP schema; characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or text strings within braces); or lossless XML (TEI P5, characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or TEI g elements).</p>
            <p>Keying and markup guidelines are available at the <ref target="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/.">Text Creation Partnership web site</ref>.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <listPrefixDef>
            <prefixDef ident="tcp"
                       matchPattern="([0-9\-]+):([0-9IVX]+)"
                       replacementPattern="http://eebo.chadwyck.com/downloadtiff?vid=$1&amp;page=$2"/>
            <prefixDef ident="char"
                       matchPattern="(.+)"
                       replacementPattern="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/textcreationpartnership/Texts/master/tcpchars.xml#$1"/>
         </listPrefixDef>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="eng">eng</language>
         </langUsage>
         <textClass>
            <keywords scheme="http://authorities.loc.gov/">
               <term>London (England) --  History --  17th century --  Early works to 1800.</term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change>
            <date>2010-04</date>
            <label>TCP</label>Assigned for keying and markup</change>
         <change>
            <date>2010-05</date>
            <label>SPi Global</label>Keyed and coded from ProQuest page images</change>
         <change>
            <date>2010-07</date>
            <label>Ali Jakobson</label>Sampled and proofread</change>
         <change>
            <date>2010-07</date>
            <label>Ali Jakobson</label>Text and markup reviewed and edited</change>
         <change>
            <date>2011-06</date>
            <label>pfs</label>Batch review (QC) and XML conversion</change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text xml:lang="eng">
      <front>
         <div type="title_page">
            <pb facs="tcp:13094:1" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <p>Londons Miſerie, THE Countryes Crueltie: WITH <hi>GODS MERCIE.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Explained by remarkeable <hi>obſerua<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions of each of them, during</hi> this laſt Viſitation.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>VVritten by</hi> Richard Milton.</p>
            <figure>
               <figDesc>printer's or publisher's device</figDesc>
            </figure>
            <p>
               <hi>LONDON,</hi> Printed by <hi>Nicholas Okes.</hi> 1625.</p>
         </div>
         <div type="dedication">
            <pb facs="tcp:13094:2"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:13094:2"/>
            <head>To his deere and louing Vnkle, Maiſter <hi>Richard Gough, of the Citty of</hi> Hereford Gentleman.</head>
            <opener>
               <salute>GOOD SIR,</salute>
            </opener>
            <p>
               <seg rend="decorInit">H</seg>Auing compoſed theſe few lines enſuing, by way of obſeruation of this preſent Viſita<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion, being an Eye-witneſſe thereof; Doe humbly preſent the ſame to your view: If there be ought ſhall giue you content, I haue my deſire; Accept my poore Labors, I pray you, So ſhall I not onely thinke it and time well ſpent, but ſhall further be encouraged to imploy the ſame hereafter, as occaſion ſhall be offered. So with my prayers to the Al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mighty for the health and proſperitie of you and yours, I remaine till death</p>
            <closer>
               <signed>
                  <hi>Your Louing Kinſeman,</hi> Richard Milton.</signed>
            </closer>
         </div>
      </front>
      <body>
         <div type="poem">
            <pb facs="tcp:13094:3"/>
            <pb n="1" facs="tcp:13094:3"/>
            <head>Londons Miſerie, The Countreys Cruelty, with Gods Mercy.</head>
            <lg>
               <l>
                  <seg rend="decorInit">N</seg>O farre fetcht Story brought from Forraigne land,</l>
               <l>Or ſuch like matters doe I take in hand;</l>
               <l>No loue ſicke Sonnet, or ſweete roundelayes,</l>
               <l>No Epigrams or ſuch like pleaſing toyes,</l>
               <l>Nor doe I write the deedes of Martiall men,</l>
               <l>That haue bin done the place, time, where and when:</l>
               <l>This I referre vnto ſome other men,</l>
               <l>To paint and ſet forth with their fluent pen:</l>
               <l>Whilſt I with ſighing doe moſt ſadly ſing,</l>
               <l>The fearefull iudgements of the Heauenly King,</l>
               <l>That in his wrath by his moſt heauy hand,</l>
               <l>Puts to amazement this moſt ſinnefull Land;</l>
               <l>A taske too hard for me, whoſe ſlender skill,</l>
               <l>Is farre vnfit, although Gods knowes my will,</l>
               <l>Be very good for matter it befits,</l>
               <l>The induſtrious penning of more curious wits:</l>
               <l>My wit is meane, God knowes, I vnderſtand</l>
               <l>But little, and for mee to take in hand</l>
               <l>This worthy worke, I might preſume too much</l>
               <l>To meddle with; for anſwere vnto ſuch</l>
               <l>Shall ſo oppoſe me, this poore ſimple skill</l>
               <l>I here haue ſhowne, is meant by me no ill</l>
               <l>
                  <pb n="2" facs="tcp:13094:4"/>In any kind, but onely for to ſhewe,</l>
               <l>The good affection I o<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> duty owe</l>
               <l>Vnto this City, (where I haue my being)</l>
               <l>Whoſe great calamities I daily ſeeing,</l>
               <l>Makes me breake forth, and with a grieued ſoule,</l>
               <l>Her miſerable ſtate for to condole,</l>
               <l>Amongſt the reſt, ſhould I not be vnkinde?</l>
               <l>As not to ſhew griefe where ſuch cauſe I finde</l>
               <l>In th'igheſt manner, to a place I loue ſo,</l>
               <l>As none in earth more dearer, ſurely no;</l>
               <l>But in this Action wilbe ſo farre bold,</l>
               <l>Not fearing what I write ſhalbe controld.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <l>ANd firſt to thee Lord, doe I humbly bow,</l>
               <l>For pardon for our ſinnes, whoſe angry brow,</l>
               <l>Still Frownes as if no mercy thou wilt haue</l>
               <l>Vpon this City, but will ſend to Graue</l>
               <l>All the inhabitants within a little ſpace,</l>
               <l>Oh be not angry ſtill, affoord vs grace</l>
               <l>For to repent, and ſtay thine angry hand,</l>
               <l>For who thy powerfull iudgements can withſtand:</l>
               <l>Lord we haue ſinned and haue done amiſſe,</l>
               <l>Wherefore thine anger fiercely kindled is:</l>
               <l>Vpon this City vengeance thou haſt powr'd,</l>
               <l>And we like ſheepe to ſlaughter are deuour'd:</l>
               <l>Our ſinnes forgiue, behold our watrie eyes,</l>
               <l>Our grieuous grones, our lamentable cryes;</l>
               <l>Long haue we fighed, but thou haſt not heard,</l>
               <l>Oft haue we prayed, but thou haſt not ſpar'd,</l>
               <l>As if euen with our prayers thou wer't offended,</l>
               <l>As if thy iudgements neuer would be ended.</l>
               <l>
                  <pb n="3" facs="tcp:13094:4"/>Faintneſſe poſſeſſeth all our vitall parts,</l>
               <l>Our courage failes vs, daunted are our hearts:</l>
               <l>In this extremity, whether ſhall we flye,</l>
               <l>But vnto thee oh God, proſtrate we lye,</l>
               <l>Before thy Throne of grace, and with bleeding wound,</l>
               <l>And ſobbing ſighes, our miſeries we ſound:</l>
               <l>Do we not know Lord thou didſt fend thy Sonne,</l>
               <l>To paie a ranſome for our deedes miſ-done,</l>
               <l>Euen from the Heauens, where thou ſies aboue,</l>
               <l>So deare the life of ſinners thou didſt loue:</l>
               <l>And when by our tranſgreſſion, mankind all,</l>
               <l>Were ſubiect to thy wrath, faſt bound and thrall;</l>
               <l>And we beleeue, Lord helpe our vnbeleefe,</l>
               <l>For of the ſame thou art our ſtay and chiefe</l>
               <l>Prop and vpholder, we beleeue I ſay,</l>
               <l>For on ſo ſure a ground ſafe build we may:</l>
               <l>VVhat thou haſt promiſde in thy ſacred Word,</l>
               <l>VVhat thou haſt vowed, oh moſt gracious Lord,</l>
               <l>That thou the death of ſinners not deſireſt,</l>
               <l>But rather life to them, for thou requireſt,</l>
               <l>That of their ſinnefull liues, they would amend,</l>
               <l>And ſo gaine mercie where they did offend:</l>
               <l>VVith patience therefore we attend thy will,</l>
               <l>Not doubting but thy words thou wilt fulfill.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <l>TIs not vnknowne to many a Forraine Nation,</l>
               <l>The beautie of <hi>London,</hi> and the ſcituation,</l>
               <l>The ſtrength, the wealth and multitude of men</l>
               <l>It did containe, at ſuch good time as when,</l>
               <l>God was at peace with vs, the Famous Sparkes</l>
               <l>Of ſweete inuention, and the learned Clarkes,</l>
               <l>
                  <pb n="4" facs="tcp:13094:5"/>VVorthy Diuines and Phiſitions ſtore,</l>
               <l>Attournes, Counſellors and pen-men more</l>
               <l>I thinke then need is, there the reuerend Iudges</l>
               <l>Gaue many a ſentence, at which ill men grudges,</l>
               <l>For there the Courts of juſtice haue bin kept,</l>
               <l>Where many a Client hath full ſorely wept.</l>
               <l>The cauſe is knowne to God, what ſhall I ſay,</l>
               <l>That to this City in ſome ſort I may</l>
               <l>Expreſſ good will, there 'twas the liberall Arts</l>
               <l>Did chieflie flouriſh, men of excellent parts</l>
               <l>Did there abide, as being the very Spring,</l>
               <l>That to their Studies ſweete refreſh did bring.</l>
               <l>There liu'd our King, alſo his noble Peeres,</l>
               <l>To whom the Lord grant life and many yeares,</l>
               <l>Of happineſſe on earth, fame and renowne,</l>
               <l>And in the end an euerlaſting Crowne</l>
               <l>Of glorie, there his Subiects at commaund,</l>
               <l>In multitude were like vnto the ſand,</l>
               <l>That on the Sea ſhore, Sea men vſe to ſee,</l>
               <l>VVhen waues are paſt, and waters calmed be:</l>
               <l>The ſeuerall ſorts of Trades-men and of Arts,</l>
               <l>The ſeuerall merchandize from Forraine parts,</l>
               <l>The multitude of rich and wealthy men,</l>
               <l>I am not able to expreſſe with pen;</l>
               <l>And though for foure yeares paſt, it ſo fell out</l>
               <l>That many Tradeſ-men here, were in great doubt</l>
               <l>They ſhould haue bin vndone, (for trading fail'd,</l>
               <l>And ſo long time their hearts were cold and quaild)</l>
               <l>Yet the late marriage of our Royall King,</l>
               <l>VVe thought a ſetling to this Realme would bring,</l>
               <l>In ſuch a wiſe, that now our feare was paſt,</l>
               <l>And well was he that did hold out till laſt,</l>
               <l>
                  <pb n="5" facs="tcp:13094:5"/>That all men ſo with doings ſhould abound,</l>
               <l>That worke-men for our worke would nere be found,</l>
               <l>Oh God, how of our hopes we are deceiued,</l>
               <l>And of our long expected ioyes bereaued,</l>
               <l>How thou our fooliſh wiſdome ſets at nought,</l>
               <l>And euen our ſelues vnto deſtruction brought,</l>
               <l>Vaine is the helpe of man, alſo are vayne</l>
               <l>The imagination of a mortall braine;</l>
               <l>Oh <hi>London, London,</hi> thou didſt feele the Rod,</l>
               <l>But neuer rightly lookt vp to thy God</l>
               <l>That ſtrook thee with it, when thou feltſt the ſmart,</l>
               <l>Euen at the firſt, then with a grieued heart,</l>
               <l>Thou of thy grieuous ſinnes ſhouldſt haue repented,</l>
               <l>And ſo Gods angry Iudgements haue preuented:</l>
               <l>This was neglected, and O moſt vnkinde,</l>
               <l>Gods former benefits imprint in minde</l>
               <l>Thou didſts not doe, for aſſuredly,</l>
               <l>Before thy wickedneſſe to him did cry</l>
               <l>For heauie vengeance, he was wondrous kinde</l>
               <l>To thee, and thou didſt many fauours finde</l>
               <l>From him, we are apt to forget God wot,</l>
               <l>Or if we doe remember, we beare not</l>
               <l>The thankfull minds we ſhould, and therefore we</l>
               <l>Euen for our ſinnes moſt iuſtly plagued be:</l>
               <l>Should we perſwade our ſelues Almighty Ioue,</l>
               <l>This Famous City did mor deerely loue,</l>
               <l>Then others, that his power could not withſtand,</l>
               <l>But in the former ages felt his hand:</l>
               <l>Or ſhall we thinke that ſhortned is his Arme,</l>
               <l>Or that he will not ſuffer ſo much harme</l>
               <l>To come vpon vs as he did to thoſe</l>
               <l>That ſinn'd aſwell as we, O, no repoſe,</l>
               <l>
                  <pb n="6" facs="tcp:13094:6"/>Nor harbor in your hearts ſo vaine a thought,</l>
               <l>For euen as they were to deſtruction brought:</l>
               <l>Euen ſo ſhall we if we do ſtill offend,</l>
               <l>And do not of our ſinfull liues amend,</l>
               <l>For as the Lord is by his mercy knowne,</l>
               <l>To be a gracious God, and he hath ſhewne</l>
               <l>That in his mercy he doth farre ſurpaſſe,</l>
               <l>Which plainely doth appeare, but yet whereas</l>
               <l>Almighty God in mercy doth abound,</l>
               <l>Take this for certaine and a conſtant ground,</l>
               <l>As on his mercies we may boldly truſt,</l>
               <l>So in his Iudgements is he alwayes iuſt.</l>
               <l>Aye me! I need not long to treate of this,</l>
               <l>How many demonſtrations dayly is,</l>
               <l>How many ſeuerall bels do ſadly ring</l>
               <l>The dolefull tune of this moſt certaine thing,</l>
               <l>In this our preſent ſad diſaſtrous plight,</l>
               <l>Whilſt many ſoules haue bid the world godnight.</l>
               <l>My fleſh do tremble, I amazed ſtand,</l>
               <l>To ſee the force of Gods Almighty hand,</l>
               <l>My hand do quake, and eke my ioynts do ſhiuer,</l>
               <l>To ſee what deadly Arrowes from his Quiuer,</l>
               <l>Are now ſent forth to this forſaken Citty,</l>
               <l>Whoſe very miſeries my ſoule doth pitty.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <l>GO on my muſe now, and right ſadly tell,</l>
               <l>The dolefull ſound that euery Pariſh bell,</l>
               <l>Within this poore aflicted Cittie make,</l>
               <l>That we may from our ſinfull liues awake:</l>
               <l>Our daily ſorrowes, and continuall feares,</l>
               <l>Our loſſe of deere friends, and our daily teares:</l>
               <l>
                  <pb n="7" facs="tcp:13094:6"/>That we for them do ſhed, the ſundry moanes,</l>
               <l>Deepe hearted ſighings, and the gricuous groanes,</l>
               <l>That many a huſband for his tender wife,</l>
               <l>Sends forth for her that is bereau'd of life:</l>
               <l>How many a wife mournes for her Turtle mate,</l>
               <l>That now lyes gaſping, ſtrucke by cruell fate</l>
               <l>Of conquering Death, and when thou haft ſo done,</l>
               <l>Tell how the father grieues for his loſt ſonne:</l>
               <l>The wofull ſcreeches many a mother mild,</l>
               <l>Bitterly ſends forth for her dying child,</l>
               <l>How many a ſonne weepes for his louing father,</l>
               <l>(Whoſe loue ſo deere was that he would more rather</l>
               <l>Haue dyde himſelfe, euen ſuch was his good will,</l>
               <l>But we cannot our owne deſires fullfill)</l>
               <l>How many a daughter grieues for her deer mother,</l>
               <l>And many a ſiſter for her louing brother,</l>
               <l>And many a brother for his louing ſiſter,</l>
               <l>That knew not what he loſt before he miſt her:</l>
               <l>Here weepes the ſeruant for his louing Maiſter,</l>
               <l>And grieues that Death is growne ſo great a waſter,</l>
               <l>There ſighes the Maiſter for his louing man,</l>
               <l>For that he is not able, neither can</l>
               <l>Saue his poore ſeruants life, with weeping eyes</l>
               <l>The carefull mayden for her Miſtreſſe cryes:</l>
               <l>The miſtreſſe likewiſe for her maide doth moane,</l>
               <l>Becauſe ſo good a ſeruant's dead and gone.</l>
               <l>Neighbour for neighbor, one friend for another,</l>
               <l>Their loues were ſuch, their griefes they cannot ſmother,</l>
               <l>The Preacher for his flocke, and they for him,</l>
               <l>We waile and weepe vntill our eyes are dim,</l>
               <l>And then, O Lord, a ſad thing for to ſee,</l>
               <l>Yet dayly ſuch ſad ſpectacles there be,</l>
               <l>
                  <pb n="8" facs="tcp:13094:7"/>They that before, ſo ſadly moumed haue,</l>
               <l>By other Friends are ſhortly brought to graue</l>
               <l>VVith much adoe, for Friends are very few,</l>
               <l>In this their laſt farewell, their loues to ſhew.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <l>SVch is the force of Deaths fell conquering hand,</l>
               <l>That none in this world can his power withſtand,</l>
               <l>Tis not the power of a mighty King,</l>
               <l>Can ſerue to free him from Deaths deadly ſting,</l>
               <l>Much leſſe the title of a Lord or Knight,</l>
               <l>Can keepe their perſons from this pale-fac't wight,</l>
               <l>Tis not the wiſedome of a learned man,</l>
               <l>No, there is neither Arte nor wiſedome can,</l>
               <l>Be forcible enough with Arte or wile,</l>
               <l>Eyther to ſtay deaths ſtroke or him beguile:</l>
               <l>Marke it I pray you, how he makes men reele,</l>
               <l>His Bow is iron ſure, and his Arrowes ſteele:</l>
               <l>How many through his might doe daily dye,</l>
               <l>How many likewiſe doe there ſprawling lye,</l>
               <l>How many alſo dead in fields are found,</l>
               <l>And ſuddainly in ſtreetes doſall to ground,</l>
               <l>Euen as they paſſe, and then before were well,</l>
               <l>And felt but little paine vntill they fell.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <l>STay gentle death, for I aſſure you can,</l>
               <l>The parties held an vpright honeſt man,</l>
               <l>You are about to deale, I tell you more,</l>
               <l>Of wealth he hath a great aboundant ſtore,</l>
               <l>And liberally he giueth to the poore</l>
               <l>Of that he hath, the like giuen at his doore,</l>
               <l>
                  <pb n="9" facs="tcp:13094:7"/>There's very few that doth, nay, hardly any,</l>
               <l>Although there doe in wealth ſurpaſſe him many.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <l>I, That is well done, I commend you better,</l>
               <l>And for your kindneſſe will remaine your debtor,</l>
               <l>That miſerable, griping, ruſty Chuffe,</l>
               <l>That alwayes wanted, neuer had enough,</l>
               <l>And neuer car'd how many men were kild,</l>
               <l>So he might haue his Cofers ſtuft and fild,</l>
               <l>Ah wr tched Carle, I truſt that there is none</l>
               <l>True hearted wight will weep when thou art gone,</l>
               <l>They in thy life time wept, and were not heard,</l>
               <l>Now at thy death they rightly may be ſpar'd.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <l>KNow you what you haue done, y'aue flaine a woman,</l>
               <l>That for her vertuous carriage, I thinke no man</l>
               <l>VVill finde the like againe, now good Sir tell,</l>
               <l>To take the good away, doe you do well:</l>
               <l>Doth there not many an idle Goſſip ſtay?</l>
               <l>VVho long before wee'd faine haue had away,</l>
               <l>Leaue of for ſhame, away now get you gone</l>
               <l>Goe take the worſt ſort, leaue the beſt alone.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <l>LOrd if 'twere ſo, what would become of me,</l>
               <l>That know my ſelfe to be as bad may be,</l>
               <l>For there's not onely one, but thouſands more,</l>
               <l>That I goe farre behind that went before,</l>
               <l>Many a braue Scholler; many a worthy Teacher,</l>
               <l>Many a good liuer, many a zealous Preacher,</l>
               <l>
                  <pb n="10" facs="tcp:13094:8"/>That liu'd as lights, and were to thee right deare,</l>
               <l>So carefully they walked in thy feare,</l>
               <l>But I alas, haue much abuſde thy will,</l>
               <l>Had not a care, thy heſts for to fulfill,</l>
               <l>Haue ſinn'd extreamly, and aſſuredly,</l>
               <l>Had long before this time, deſeru'd to dye;</l>
               <l>But yet, O Lord, I ſee 'tis not thy will,</l>
               <l>Thou ſpar'ſt my life, wilt haue me tarry ſtill.</l>
               <l>And now I pray thee, whilſt I haue my being,</l>
               <l>Sith that thou haſt vouchſaft to me the ſeeing,</l>
               <l>(Wretch that I am) of this thy mighty power,</l>
               <l>Grant that hereafter, daily and each houre,</l>
               <l>For that ſame ſmall time, and the little ſpace</l>
               <l>Of life that thou ſhalt grant me by thy grace,</l>
               <l>I may redeeme time, which I lewdly ſpent,</l>
               <l>Bewaile my ſinnes, and heartily repent.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <l>VVHen hoary hyems now had chang'd his hue,</l>
               <l>And for that yeare had bid the world a due,</l>
               <l>When trees gan ſprout, the graſſe and euery thing</l>
               <l>Lookt greene and faire, lambes skipt, the bird; did ſing</l>
               <l>And with their warbling notes in woods did Ring</l>
               <l>Their makers prayſe, according to their kinde,</l>
               <l>
                  <hi>April</hi> the moneth was cald, for ſo I finde,</l>
               <l>(For fore that time there dyed not any ſtore,</l>
               <l>That either had the tokens or plague ſore)</l>
               <l>Then did the Lord begin to lay his hand,</l>
               <l>And plainly ſhewd he'd giue vs vnderſtand,</l>
               <l>That he was angry with vs, at the firſt</l>
               <l>Small quaintity there dy'd, Death did not thirſt</l>
               <l>As now it doth, a dozen or a ſcore:</l>
               <l>We thought it much, ſoone after forty more,</l>
               <l>
                  <pb n="11" facs="tcp:13094:8"/>Or ſuch like number to the ground were ſent,</l>
               <l>But hardly any miſſe of thoſe that went,</l>
               <l>Time ſlides away, our glaſſe doth daily runne,</l>
               <l>And God will finiſh what he had begunne,</l>
               <l>For ſhortly after in the Bills are ſpide,</l>
               <l>About a hundred of the ſickneſſe dyde:</l>
               <l>And yet at that time, I remember well,</l>
               <l>There's very few of vs could rightly tell,</l>
               <l>Whether the ſickneſſe were the plague or no,</l>
               <l>So willingly we would haue had it ſo:</l>
               <l>The Searchers now brought into queſtion be,</l>
               <l>For that poore aged folkes they could not ſee</l>
               <l>Gods handy-worke, twas thought that they did wrong</l>
               <l>To many people, thus did we prolong</l>
               <l>Our miſeries, aduice was taken then</l>
               <l>Of Phiſicke Doctors, all held worthy men,</l>
               <l>And ſuch as for their skill did much ſurpaſſe</l>
               <l>The meaner ſort; they told vs, that whereas</l>
               <l>Thoſe that from vs, this ſickneſſe did deuide,</l>
               <l>Had caught a ſpotted feuer, and ſo dyde.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <l>THus the Almightie, though he hath and can,</l>
               <l>Produce ſtrange wonders by the Arte of man,</l>
               <l>Neuertheleſſe, when he thinkes good, he will</l>
               <l>Confound the wiſedome, and the learned skill</l>
               <l>Of mortall Creatures, and vs plainly ſhew,</l>
               <l>He can ſend iudgments, that they ſhall not know</l>
               <l>How to preuent, with all their arte or skill,</l>
               <l>If we rebell, and not his will fulfill.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <pb n="12" facs="tcp:13094:9"/>
               <l>THE Former Searchers now are in hard caſe,</l>
               <l>They are reprou'd, ſome forc't to looſe their place;</l>
               <l>And now with cheerefull hearts, we doe agree,</l>
               <l>The former doubt, but a miſtake might bee;</l>
               <l>Yet ſtill alas, the ſickneſſe doth increaſe,</l>
               <l>And therefore of our feares we do not ceaſe:</l>
               <l>Thoſe that they now appoint, are bound with oath,</l>
               <l>Vpon their conſciences to tell the troth,</l>
               <l>That neither for reward, or filthy ſeare,</l>
               <l>Or elſe for any fauour that they beare</l>
               <l>Vnto the perſons that are ſo infected,</l>
               <l>Should ſtop their iudgments, now to be expected.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <l>THeir charge receiu'd, away now do they hie,</l>
               <l>And to their buſineſſe do they looke more nigh,</l>
               <l>Daies quickly go, the nights likewiſe full faſt,</l>
               <l>And very ſudainly a weeke is paſt;</l>
               <l>And now we lookt to be reſolued well,</l>
               <l>And who but ſearchers could vs betrer tell:</l>
               <l>The queſtions askt, and then they told their mind,</l>
               <l>That certainly the places which they find</l>
               <l>So viſited, ſo farre as they could ſee,</l>
               <l>No other ſicknes then the plague ſhould be.</l>
               <l>The reaſon now of this afore-ſaid doubt</l>
               <l>(As I haue heard) by experience is found out,</l>
               <l>That as the plague, beginneth with the yeare,</l>
               <l>So do the markes thereof, at firſt appeare</l>
               <l>Much like the ſpotted Feuer, as time goes on,</l>
               <l>And yeare vpon his backe, puts age vppon,</l>
               <l>The markes do alter to another hue,</l>
               <l>Leauing the red, and then is turn'd to blew.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <pb n="13" facs="tcp:13094:9"/>
               <l>VVE ſtuddy now, and often caſt about,</l>
               <l>And call to mind, what heretofore fell out,</l>
               <l>Vpon the Death of any Souerainge Prince,</l>
               <l>Or in Succeſſors raigne hath hapned ſince,</l>
               <l>There's many of vs doe remember yet</l>
               <l>It was ſo late, we can it not forget,</l>
               <l>When firſt King <hi>Iames,</hi> came here this Crowne to ſway,</l>
               <l>How many by the plague were caught away;</l>
               <l>And now the moſt of vs perſwaded be,</l>
               <l>That ſuch a ſckneſſe we againe ſhall ſee:</l>
               <l>But being come vnto the month of <hi>Iune,</hi>
               </l>
               <l>It ſings to vs a ſad and mourneſfull tune:</l>
               <l>For now we thinke, the ſickneſſe will not ceaſe,</l>
               <l>Becauſe we find it weekly doth increaſe,</l>
               <l>Orders are now preſcribde, and beſt inuention</l>
               <l>That we can vſe or finde out for preuention,</l>
               <l>The doores of ſicke are ſhut, and Dogs be kild,</l>
               <l>Tis better they ſhould goe, then we be fild</l>
               <l>With noyſome ſmells, a reaſon ſome doth tell,</l>
               <l>That brings the ſickneſſe with vs here to dwell,</l>
               <l>It to auoid, houſes and ſtreetes we waſh,</l>
               <l>And many a paile of water downe we paſh</l>
               <l>Before our doores, the place of thoſe infected,</l>
               <l>We warily auoyd, though we reſpected</l>
               <l>The viſited before their ſickneſſe came,</l>
               <l>Yet now to ſee them would redound much blame</l>
               <l>Vnto vs, all the neighbours they would ſcare vs,</l>
               <l>And hearing it, few of them would come neere vs,</l>
               <l>For ſo to doe can we tell what may chance</l>
               <l>To vs, or ours, ſo farre for to aduance,</l>
               <l>Or venture out our ſelues, them to come neare,</l>
               <l>Pray blame vs not, we iuſtly may forbeare:</l>
               <l>
                  <pb n="14" facs="tcp:13094:10"/>Thus did we feare at firſt, but time growes on,</l>
               <l>That which before we could not build vppon,</l>
               <l>
                  <hi>Trinity</hi> Terme was for that time put off,</l>
               <l>Cauſes of ſuite in Law were driuen off</l>
               <l>Till longer time, they that came many a mile</l>
               <l>VVith griefe returne, ſtay heere but little while,</l>
               <l>That hoped to haue ſeene ſome happy end</l>
               <l>O<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> their long Suites, now vainely doe they ſpend</l>
               <l>Both time and money, <hi>London</hi> they forſake,</l>
               <l>And many a long and wearie ſteppe they make,</l>
               <l>Before they come vnto their wiſht deſire,</l>
               <l>To ſee the ſmoake that iſſues from the fire</l>
               <l>Of their owne Chymneys, and to preuent</l>
               <l>Danger of infection, the Parliament,</l>
               <l>That euer commonly with vs did ſit,</l>
               <l>Do now forbeare, and thinke it farre more fit,</l>
               <l>That kept it ſhould be in ſome other place:</l>
               <l>The City <hi>Oxford</hi> 'twas that had the grace</l>
               <l>Of that aſſembly: there they time did ſpend</l>
               <l>No doubtfull carefull, for to make an end</l>
               <l>Of that they had in hand, ſtatutes are acted,</l>
               <l>And in a booke together are compacted</l>
               <l>For publique good; there let them reſt a while,</l>
               <l>Whilſt we goe forwards in our homelie ſtile,</l>
               <l>To tell you truely what did come to paſſe</l>
               <l>To moneth next following which cald <hi>Iuly</hi> was:</l>
               <l>Each weeke with longing we deſire to ſee</l>
               <l>VVhither the bills increaſt or leſſened be,</l>
               <l>But where the figures ſet for hundreds were,</l>
               <l>Now thouſands three and more there do appeare,</l>
               <l>By hundreds three, foure ſcore fiue in number,</l>
               <l>Due time it is for vs to leaue of ſlumber:</l>
               <l>
                  <pb n="15" facs="tcp:13094:10"/>And generally with one voyce and accord,</l>
               <l>We gin to weigh the iudgments of the Lord,</l>
               <l>And ſeeke to him, our helper and our guide,</l>
               <l>That we of mercie may not be denide</l>
               <l>In this affliction, call to minde our ſinne</l>
               <l>VVith humble praiers and faſting we beginne,</l>
               <l>That ſo we may appeaſe Gods angrie hand,</l>
               <l>(The onely way his iudgements to withſtand)</l>
               <l>Wherein aſſuredlie we did doe well,</l>
               <l>VVe knew the gracious goodnes which befell</l>
               <l>To <hi>Niniue,</hi> and other Cities noe,</l>
               <l>Which elſe had bin deſtroyd, had't not bin ſo</l>
               <l>They had repented, this right godly thing,</l>
               <l>Firſt was commended by our noble King,</l>
               <l>Thereby he ſhew'd, that he a Father was</l>
               <l>Vnto this Citie, and what came to paſſe</l>
               <l>He tooke to heart, alas what better loue,</l>
               <l>Or friend for friendſhip can we further prooue,</l>
               <l>Then at ſuch times, as we afflicted be,</l>
               <l>That they are moou'd our miſeries to ſee,</l>
               <l>And do their beſt endeauors, to be briefe,</l>
               <l>Vſe all the arte they can for our reliefe.</l>
               <l>In this renowned King, great commendation</l>
               <l>We muſt aſcribe, welfare and preſeruation</l>
               <l>Of vs and ours was dailie in thy minde,</l>
               <l>As by thy prouident care we did it finde:</l>
               <l>Should we vnthankfull be, it were moſt vild,</l>
               <l>And we hereafter iuſtly might be ſtild</l>
               <l>Vngratefull ſubiects, likewiſe know 'twas he,</l>
               <l>Gaue ſpeciall order that a booke ſhould be</l>
               <l>Read in our Faſts of Prayers, and Pſalmes ſelected</l>
               <l>Fit for the times, ſo greatly he reſpected</l>
               <l>
                  <pb n="16" facs="tcp:13094:11"/>The ſafetie of our ſoules; another Booke</l>
               <l>By him was fet forth, wherein if you looke,</l>
               <l>Medcines for bodies health did there inſert,</l>
               <l>With wary viſements, how we ſhould diuert</l>
               <l>Or keepe our ſelues from cauſes of Infection,</l>
               <l>VVhat elſe to do he gaue to vs direction.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <l>BVt well-away, before the moneth is gone,</l>
               <l>How many thouſands, left vs here alone,</l>
               <l>And gaue vs leaue to faſt, and eke to pray,</l>
               <l>For neither wealth nor Counſell could them ſtay;</l>
               <l>Both rich and poore, away now doe they hye,</l>
               <l>Both old and young, they care not where they lye,</l>
               <l>In barnes, or hay-cockes, fields, or vnder tree,</l>
               <l>Nor how they fare, ſo <hi>London</hi> they not ſee.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <l>
                  <hi>LOndon</hi> that heretofore had ſuch Renowne,</l>
               <l>Is not reſpected as a common Towne,</l>
               <l>Her glories darkned and her ſtrength decayde,</l>
               <l>And thoſe that truſted in her are afraide</l>
               <l>For to come neere her, <hi>London</hi> that heretofore</l>
               <l>VVhich for the bigneſſe ſure was people more</l>
               <l>Then any City in the world againe,</l>
               <l>Doth ſay when God is angrie 'tis but vaine</l>
               <l>To truſt in multitude, but I call to minde,</l>
               <l>VVhen 't did abound with men, then moſt vnkinde,</l>
               <l>Full many of vs grudge to haue it ſo,</l>
               <l>Thinking the cauſe thereof procur'd vs woe,</l>
               <l>So many of a trade, (thus did we grieue)</l>
               <l>That one man by another could not liue;</l>
               <l>
                  <pb n="17" facs="tcp:13094:11"/>Sure God was angrie with vs, now you ſee</l>
               <l>The Citie of large multitudes are free,</l>
               <l>Where is the doings that ſhould now abound?</l>
               <l>Sure nothing elſe but wayling is there found,</l>
               <l>For want of thoſe that in the ſame did dwell,</l>
               <l>And when woe will be done we cannot tell.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <l>BVt ſhall I leaue our fellow brethren ſo,</l>
               <l>And not vouchſafe a little for to go,</l>
               <l>To bring them out of towne, at leaſt-wiſe know,</l>
               <l>The fauour iolly Country men did ſhew</l>
               <l>To ſtrangers and to kin, but fitſt alas</l>
               <l>You know tis fitting they ſhould haue a paſſe,</l>
               <l>Whither he be a wiſeman or an Aſſe,</l>
               <l>Vnleſſe he meane to lye vpon the graſſe:</l>
               <l>The which vnto the Country men they ſhew;</l>
               <l>Contents whereof doth let all people know,</l>
               <l>That where Almighty God (more is the pitty)</l>
               <l>With ſickneſſe now had viſited the Citty,</l>
               <l>Yet notwithſtanding (bleſt be his high hand,)</l>
               <l>Their dwelling houſe, amongſt the reſt doth ſtand</l>
               <l>Free from infection: nay, ſome thought it meete,</l>
               <l>To ſet downe in their writing, all the ſtreete</l>
               <l>Wherein they dwelled (prayſ'd be God) was cleare,</l>
               <l>And therefore as for that, you neede not feare</l>
               <l>To giue them entertainment; this ſafe kept,</l>
               <l>Made many that at firſt full ſweetly ſlept</l>
               <l>In wholeſome beds, and likewiſe to fare well,</l>
               <l>But afterwards it otherwiſe befell:</l>
               <l>
                  <hi>London</hi> they thought all ouer was infected,</l>
               <l>And therefore they no paſſes now reſpected.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <pb n="16" facs="tcp:13094:12"/>
               <l>VVAndring in Fields, ſome here, ſome there do lye,</l>
               <l>And by the way there's many of them die,</l>
               <l>A grieuous ſpectacle for to behold,</l>
               <l>And cauſing teares may for to heare it told,</l>
               <l>To ſee that Chriſtians ſhould be ſo eſtrang'd,</l>
               <l>And from their marke Chriſtianitie ſo rang'd,</l>
               <l>That from another they no loue can haue,</l>
               <l>So farre as to vouchſafe them to their graue,</l>
               <l>But leaue them merciles, eu'n where they die,</l>
               <l>And ſo expoſe them to the rauenous eie</l>
               <l>Of Foules and other vermine, verie vnfit,</l>
               <l>And ſurely ſhewes ſmall loue, or little wit</l>
               <l>In theſe our Countrie-men; but I alas,</l>
               <l>Am gone too farre with you, how ſhall I paſſe</l>
               <l>From whence I came, you know I am expected;</l>
               <l>And let not <hi>London</hi> be by me neglected.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <l>FAſts are continued, <hi>Wenſday</hi> is the daie,</l>
               <l>And many of vs I dare boldly ſay,</l>
               <l>Did carefully obſerue them, many moe,</l>
               <l>(I do perſwade me) did not keep them ſo</l>
               <l>As fit they ſhould, 'tis goodly for to ſee,</l>
               <l>How yet our Churcher fild with people be,</l>
               <l>And with attention do the Preacher heare,</l>
               <l>Although ſo many durſt not venture there,</l>
               <l>For feare of further harme, I neuer heard</l>
               <l>Such zealous Preaching that was ſtill conferd</l>
               <l>Vnto the hearers; braue renowned men</l>
               <l>That ſo encourag'd vs, I would my pen</l>
               <l>Had all the arte that might be to giue praiſe,</l>
               <l>Vnto your worthy actions; many waies</l>
               <l>
                  <pb n="19" facs="tcp:13094:12"/>You did declare your ſelues like Champions ſtout,</l>
               <l>And were the only men that held vs out</l>
               <l>From fainting, Phyſitions they were fled,</l>
               <l>Onely a few amongſt the reſt, ſome dead,</l>
               <l>And griefe to ſpeake, but true it is (God wot,)</l>
               <l>Of your owne Coate too many tarried not:</l>
               <l>To thoſe that ſtaid then, you gaine double praiſe,</l>
               <l>For taking paines when <hi>Halcion</hi> were our daies,</l>
               <l>And ſticke not now your liues for vs to ſpend,</l>
               <l>Euen your owne bloods, ſo that you might but end</l>
               <l>Twixt God and vs the ſtrife, this was your care,</l>
               <l>Thus <hi>Moſes</hi> humbly ſought the Lord to ſpare</l>
               <l>Hard hearted Iewes, full often was he heard,</l>
               <l>And I perſwade my ſelfe God hath not bard</l>
               <l>Sweet mercies gate ſo faſt, but one time he</l>
               <l>Or other with our prayers will pleaſed be:</l>
               <l>Go on therefore, ſurely of God y'bleſt,</l>
               <l>And let not the Almighty yet take reſt,</l>
               <l>Vntill that by his mercies we do finde</l>
               <l>Gods wrath appea<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>de, and he of other minde.</l>
               <l>And next on earth then you ſhall haue the praiſe,</l>
               <l>Men, wiues and children, ſhall with pleaſing laies,</l>
               <l>Haue cauſe to ſing your Victories about,</l>
               <l>And ſay you were their Champions fell and ſtout,</l>
               <l>That <hi>Iacob</hi> like did wraſtle with the Lord,</l>
               <l>And held him faſt vntill he did affoord</l>
               <l>To hold his hand, and this great ſickneſſe ſtay,</l>
               <l>This may be ſaid of you another day.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <l>ALthough the Sunne ſhinde bright, the Heauens faire,</l>
               <l>Yet ſtill we thought corrupted was the ayre,</l>
               <l>
                  <pb n="20" facs="tcp:13094:13"/>Great cauſe it was of ſickneſſe, ſo we thought,</l>
               <l>And ſo by learned writers were we tought:</l>
               <l>It to auoide, the beſt aduice we take,</l>
               <l>To cleere the <hi>Ayre,</hi> great <hi>Boneſiers</hi> we make</l>
               <l>Before our doores, as likewiſe pans of fire</l>
               <l>Ymixt with pitch, ſo greatly we deſire</l>
               <l>Cauſe of Infections ceaſe, then thought it meete,</l>
               <l>That euery one at home, or elſe in ſtreete</l>
               <l>(As they did paſſe) ſhould to a Noſe-gay ſmell</l>
               <l>Held in their hands, which would do very well:</l>
               <l>Some made of Hempe &amp; Pitch, others thought fit</l>
               <l>To vſe ſome other Sents, which I omit.</l>
               <l>And Franckenſence in houſes do we burne,</l>
               <l>And vſe all other meanes we can to turne</l>
               <l>That into ſweete we thought corrupted was,</l>
               <l>Lets leaue off this and tell what came to paſſe.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <l>ANd now imagine <hi>Iuly</hi> we haue paſt,</l>
               <l>
                  <hi>Auguſt</hi> the Moneth is, wherein we ſo faſt</l>
               <l>Do leaue this world, to ſeeke another reſt,</l>
               <l>Where in one weeke there died at the leaſt</l>
               <l>Fiue thouſand ſoules, two hundreth and fiue,</l>
               <l>They'd make a faire ſhew to be ſeene aliue:</l>
               <l>So many thouſands in the Country gone,</l>
               <l>And we ſo few in number left alone,</l>
               <l>And yet ſo many in one weeke ſhould dye,</l>
               <l>So many courſes, that I thinke nere eye</l>
               <l>Did ere behold dayly and howerly paſſe</l>
               <l>Within this Citty, infinite griefe alas,</l>
               <l>Muſt needes poſſeſſe thoſe that are left aliue,</l>
               <l>And for our ſafeguard, how do we now ſtriue,</l>
               <l>
                  <pb n="21" facs="tcp:13094:13"/>Theſe lines enſuing will directly tell,</l>
               <l>Pleaſe you peruſe them and to marke them well.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <l>THe eighteenth of the month that was the weeke,</l>
               <l>Now not ſo much for humaine helpes we ſeeke,</l>
               <l>But ready for Deaths ſtroake we do prepare,</l>
               <l>And for to gaine heauens Crowne is all our care:</l>
               <l>Daily we ſee our Friends and neighbours dye,</l>
               <l>And who can ſay is next, ore he or I:</l>
               <l>The ſhunning now of ſicke is not reſpected,</l>
               <l>For who doth know whoſe houſe is not infected,</l>
               <l>They are not now pent vp, doores are open,</l>
               <l>No coy there is with any to be ſpoken,</l>
               <l>But one with other do conſort together,</l>
               <l>And as for danger few of vs care whether,</l>
               <l>The partie we are with be ſicke or no,</l>
               <l>Onely we aske him whether it be ſo;</l>
               <l>And where the paine proceedes, riſing or ſpot,</l>
               <l>And to their beds we go, for we are not</l>
               <l>So timerous; but do approach them neere,</l>
               <l>And with our beſt aduiſe we do them cheere;</l>
               <l>And being dead now we ſuch kindneſſe haue,</l>
               <l>None will refuſe to bring them to the graue,</l>
               <l>But after Beeres we throng without diſdaine,</l>
               <l>And in our iudgement hold it very vaine,</l>
               <l>If we ſhould not our laſt performance lend</l>
               <l>To ſuch a neighbour or to ſuch a Friend,</l>
               <l>Diſcourteous, vnfit and eke faint-hearted,</l>
               <l>Thus did we meete and thus we kindly parted.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <pb n="22" facs="tcp:13094:14"/>
               <l>VVEll may I ſay to many a Country lout</l>
               <l>Of this our Kingdome, where's the valour ſtout</l>
               <l>Poſſeſt your fearefull hearts? what is the matter</l>
               <l>That ſo for feare your very teeth do chatter</l>
               <l>VVithin your heads, why do your bones ſo ſhiuer?</l>
               <l>As if you neyther had nor heart nor liuer:</l>
               <l>To ſee a <hi>London</hi> man, oh y'are vndone,</l>
               <l>Venture not neere, but as farre from him runne,</l>
               <l>As Furlongs two containe at leaſt, oh flye,</l>
               <l>His very breath will ſmell, as farre as eye</l>
               <l>Can ere behold him: are you not a ſham'd,</l>
               <l>And in all good mens iudgements to be blam'd:</l>
               <l>I am not ignorant of your churliſh dealing,</l>
               <l>The wound that open is, will need long healing</l>
               <l>Of your vnkindneſſe ſhew'd to our poore City:</l>
               <l>Hard hearted men, you ſhould haue had more pitty.</l>
               <l>You thinke vs Cowards, you the worthies are,</l>
               <l>And who but you, for ſturdie men of warre:</l>
               <l>How is it now, doe you not plainly ſee,</l>
               <l>
                  <hi>London</hi> doth yeeld as ſtout as any he,</l>
               <l>Liues on your clotted grounds, as doe appeare,</l>
               <l>We ſtand not in ſuch dread, nor do we feare</l>
               <l>The loſſe of our poore lifes, for in a word,</l>
               <l>Although we in a manner ſee the ſword,</l>
               <l>Of the Almighties Iuſtice euer wauing</l>
               <l>Ouer our heads, killing many crauing,</l>
               <l>Yet from the venger do we neuer ſhrinke,</l>
               <l>No we perſwaded be and ſurely thinke,</l>
               <l>That he is euery where and that he can,</l>
               <l>(And if pleaſe him) ſend to the Country man,</l>
               <l>As great a ſickneſſe as he hath to vs,</l>
               <l>Thus I perſwade my ſelfe and euen thus</l>
               <l>
                  <pb n="23" facs="tcp:13094:14"/>Should you perſwaded be and vnderſtand,</l>
               <l>That the beſt meanes for to auoyd God hand,</l>
               <l>Is not to flye, but to approach him neere</l>
               <l>With heartie ſorrow, take heed how we we beare</l>
               <l>Our ſelues hereafter that we not offend,</l>
               <l>Elſe worſer iudgements God to vs can ſend</l>
               <l>VVhere ere we be, with you I haue now done:</l>
               <l>Lord with what longing do the people runne,</l>
               <l>To know what number this next weeke haue dyde,</l>
               <l>And now (bleſt be his name) we haue eſpide</l>
               <l>A happy ceaſing of his anger paſt,</l>
               <l>For in this weeke they dyed not ſo faſt:</l>
               <l>Foure thouſand, eight hundred, one and forty fell,</l>
               <l>Though a great number, it reioyſt vs well</l>
               <l>To ſee a ceaſing, and with thankfull minde,</l>
               <l>VVe gaue Gods thankes for that he was ſo kinde;</l>
               <l>And by the way now this is to be noted,</l>
               <l>And will be markt by thoſe that are deuoted,</l>
               <l>When we were now euen hurl'd into deſpaire</l>
               <l>And ſcarſe car'd whether day was foule or faire,</l>
               <l>Such a perplexity were wee driuen in,</l>
               <l>That how the world went we weigh'd not a pin,</l>
               <l>VVhen we were almoſt weare now with crying,</l>
               <l>And almoſt paſt all hope for ought relying</l>
               <l>At the Almighties hands, loe euen then,</l>
               <l>He gan to ſhew vnto vs (ſinfull men)</l>
               <l>Some tokens, that his anger will not long</l>
               <l>Continue, if ſo be wee ſing the ſong</l>
               <l>Of true repentance. I remember well</l>
               <l>The Prohibition of our faſt daies fell</l>
               <l>This very weeke, the ceaſing was before,</l>
               <l>VVe cannot then directly ſay therefore,</l>
               <l>
                  <pb n="24" facs="tcp:13094:15"/>That they were cauſe ſo many were infected,</l>
               <l>I hope there's few that are ſo ill affected</l>
               <l>As ſo to thinke; did we not meete together,</l>
               <l>And as I ſayd before, we car'd not whether</l>
               <l>Daily and hourely 'bout our worldly ends,</l>
               <l>Some one for one thing, others ſee their Friends</l>
               <l>Lye viſited: ſicke with well we mingle,</l>
               <l>Thoſe that are well from ſicke we cannot ſingle,</l>
               <l>Yet many of vs were both well and ſound,</l>
               <l>And I amongſt the reſt this fauour found;</l>
               <l>(Bleſt be his holy name) no more of this,</l>
               <l>Now in my minde a home-bred ſtory is,</l>
               <l>Of one I knew, a Country-man of mine,</l>
               <l>(Hardly deſeruing here to haue a line)</l>
               <l>Who did refraine the Church (ſo wiſe was he)</l>
               <l>So did his ſonne leſt they infect might be:</l>
               <l>VVhat I inſert I heard it to be true,</l>
               <l>And I thinke God their iudgment gaue them due,</l>
               <l>Neyther in Church or Church yard did they dye,</l>
               <l>But in the open Fields there did they lye.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <l>ANd one thing more I thought good to obſerue,</l>
               <l>Whether it obſeruation do deſerue,</l>
               <l>Or no I pray you iudge, this did I find,</l>
               <l>When we vnto each other were moſt kind,</l>
               <l>And feared not the viſited to ſee,</l>
               <l>Yet euen at that time I noted we</l>
               <l>Did find a ceaſing, which did plainly ſhew,</l>
               <l>That we vnto the Almighty much did owe</l>
               <l>For his great loue, beyond imagination,</l>
               <l>And farre beyond all humaine expectation:</l>
               <l>
                  <pb n="25" facs="tcp:13094:15"/>For fore that time moſt were of iudgement ſtill,</l>
               <l>The reaſon why ſo many there were ill,</l>
               <l>VVas cauſe they tooke not heed, nor much reſpected,</l>
               <l>To keepe themſelues from thoſe that were infected;</l>
               <l>The laſt great ſickneſſe it did fall out ſo,</l>
               <l>(As I haue heard) well let vs forwards goe,</l>
               <l>Not that I thinke the ſickneſſe not infect,</l>
               <l>For many then my iudgement will reiect,</l>
               <l>For to the contrary it doth appeare,</l>
               <l>Therfore i'de wiſh no mortall wight come neere</l>
               <l>Infected perſons to preſume too much,</l>
               <l>Vnleſſe occaſions ſo great be ſuch,</l>
               <l>As eyther them to helpe or helpe themſelues,</l>
               <l>Elſe ſhould I count them for preſuming Elues.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <l>VVEarie with toyle and with ſad cares oppreſt,</l>
               <l>Let now my muſe from this ſad ſtraine take reft,</l>
               <l>Neuertheleſſe but for a little while,</l>
               <l>And giue me leaue but onely for to ſmile</l>
               <l>At worldlings folly, how with care they ſtriue</l>
               <l>To keepe their earthly Carcaſſes aliue,</l>
               <l>Whilſt others pining do deſire to dye,</l>
               <l>Reſpectleſſe of their liues, ſuch miſery</l>
               <l>They do ſuſtaine, y wrapt in cruell loue,</l>
               <l>Or elſe ſome higher croſſes from aboue,</l>
               <l>For recreation I thinke beſt befits,</l>
               <l>In time of ſadneſſe to reuiue our wits</l>
               <l>With honeſt mirth, a ſtory for to tell,</l>
               <l>The beſt I haue marke then how it befell:</l>
               <l>In <hi>Gloster ſhiere,</hi> (a parcell of this Land)</l>
               <l>There <hi>Cheltenham</hi> my natiue Towne doth ſtand,</l>
               <l>
                  <pb n="26" facs="tcp:13094:16"/>Many a braue lad hath there beene bred and bore,</l>
               <l>As well in theſe our times as long before,</l>
               <l>VVho hand to hand in battle would men thrill,</l>
               <l>Ere they from them would ſuffer any ill:</l>
               <l>Howbeit now the ſickneſſe (as I heare)</l>
               <l>Haue brought theſe hardy men into great feare:</l>
               <l>Yet to their kindred ſtill their loue is ſuch,</l>
               <l>To giue them kind reliefe they will not grutch,</l>
               <l>Prouided alwayes that they may be pent,</l>
               <l>In ſome remoted place whereas the ſent</l>
               <l>May not annoy the dwellers of the Towne,</l>
               <l>Elſe one againſt another well might frowne:</l>
               <l>Some two miles off the ſame there ſtands a hill,</l>
               <l>That if you ſaw it, ſurely ſay you will</l>
               <l>It is a great one, likewiſe very high,</l>
               <l>Not farre vpon, nor yet not very nigh</l>
               <l>A wood doth ſtand, <hi>Puckham</hi> is cald by name,</l>
               <l>And there abouts is of great note and fame</l>
               <l>In nutting time, then famous let it be</l>
               <l>A little more, for that we now do ſee,</l>
               <l>It prooues a ſhelter to our <hi>London</hi> men,</l>
               <l>VVho there did lurke as Foxes in their den,</l>
               <l>But if they chanc't abroad once for to ſtere,</l>
               <l>More dreadfull far then wolues they did appeare</l>
               <l>To friend or foe: if once they doe them ſpie,</l>
               <l>Their ſight more fell then <hi>Baſilis koes</hi> eye,</l>
               <l>There lodg'd that hard Squire Sir <hi>Henry</hi> hight,</l>
               <l>A valiant, doubty and couragious ſpright,</l>
               <l>There lay that Lady bright, his partner deare,</l>
               <l>That were moſt brauely brought on horſe-back there:</l>
               <l>With diuers others men of mickle worth,</l>
               <l>That were reſolu'd none of them to come forth,</l>
               <l>
                  <pb n="27" facs="tcp:13094:16"/>But round about the wood to roue and range,</l>
               <l>Vntill the Moone had paſt her full and change:</l>
               <l>This was the order then, but out alas,</l>
               <l>VVhilſt we on hills are, there's a <hi>London</hi> Aſſe</l>
               <l>Or Carrier comes to Towne within bow ſhot,</l>
               <l>When as the ſickneſſe raign'd exceeding hot,</l>
               <l>His packe he doth vntie, and <hi>London</hi> ware</l>
               <l>Lyes open to be catch't with <hi>Cheltnam</hi> ayre:</l>
               <l>High time it is for ſafety to prouide,</l>
               <l>More harme then ere aware may them betide,</l>
               <l>The matter knowne ſome wiſe men of the Towne,</l>
               <l>Bold affrappeth this foole hardy Clowne,</l>
               <l>With bitter threates, and with a dire aſpect,</l>
               <l>This great preſumptuous act they do detect,</l>
               <l>And to him ſpake thus or to this effect:</l>
               <l>Thou <hi>London</hi> vagrant, bold preſumptuous man,</l>
               <l>All words to good for thee that name we can,</l>
               <l>Is this a place for thee for to vntie?</l>
               <l>At ſuch a time as this, now verily,</l>
               <l>If ſtreight thou do'ſt not truſſe, and quickly runne</l>
               <l>From this ſame coaſt, weele ſhoot thee with a Gun.</l>
               <l>At which hard words forthwith it did appeare,</l>
               <l>How much it deern'd him by the trembling feare</l>
               <l>Of all his ioynts, for greatly he did quake,</l>
               <l>And ſeem'd as if his very heart did ake,</l>
               <l>Sighing, quoth he, good ſits be not offended,</l>
               <l>VVhat's done amiſſe hereafter ſhall be mended.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <l>COurage braue <hi>London,</hi> heart vnto thee take,</l>
               <l>For euery weeke the ſickneſſe now doth ſlake,</l>
               <l>
                  <pb n="28" facs="tcp:13094:17"/>What ſhall we alwayes faint, be drooping men</l>
               <l>And thinke that nere good time will come agen,</l>
               <l>Indeede 'tis true, many our Friends are gone,</l>
               <l>And deare ones too, we cannot chooſe but moane</l>
               <l>For them a while, Gods hand we cannot ſtay</l>
               <l>When he doth pleaſe to ſtrike, well wiſh we may,</l>
               <l>Time is for all, a time there is to die,</l>
               <l>And as they are ſo muſt be you and I,</l>
               <l>A debt we owe, that is to God a Death,</l>
               <l>Short is our life and ſoone gone is our breath:</l>
               <l>Here is no reſting place, Pilgrims we are</l>
               <l>VVithin this world, vnto a Country farre</l>
               <l>VVe haue to trace, it is to Heauens high,</l>
               <l>To which we cannot come before we die:</l>
               <l>They are in reſt no doubt, we ſtill in care,</l>
               <l>Sorrow we taſte, but they doe better fare.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <l>LIke as in bloody field a battell fought,</l>
               <l>By raging enemies that alwayes ſought</l>
               <l>To worke vnto each other harme and skath,</l>
               <l>And nought but death could ſwage their banefull wrath,</l>
               <l>VVhere many thouſands in one battel dye,</l>
               <l>And many groueling on the earth doe lye,</l>
               <l>After a long and weary battel tride,</l>
               <l>So many wounded eke ſo many dyde,</l>
               <l>Vpon retire they doe their loſſes count,</l>
               <l>And finde they doe in number much ſurmount,</l>
               <l>Of this poore Citie ſuch now was the caſe,</l>
               <l>When time had made ſo many runne the race</l>
               <l>Of this their mortall liues, the reſt behind</l>
               <l>To know the perfect number were inclin'd</l>
               <l>
                  <pb n="29" facs="tcp:13094:17"/>Of thoſe that dy'd the ſeuerall Bills they view,</l>
               <l>And caſt them vp to be informed true:</l>
               <l>The better to expreſſe, ceaſe Verſe a while,</l>
               <l>And let vs forwards in another ſtile.</l>
            </lg>
            <p>GEntle Reader, I am not ignorant what great mortal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lity hath beene reported, and verily beleeued to be in <hi>London,</hi> in almoſt all places of this Kingdome, by reaſon of this ſickneſſe; and that they conceiued a farre greater number dyed, then indeed there did: or at leaſt-wiſe not conſidering, or once imagining, ſuch a multitude of people, men, women and children ſhould bee in one place, or City, thought verily there were hardly any or very few of vs left a liue.</p>
            <p>Indeede the ſtreetes were empty in reſpect of the large multitudes that formerly before this great ſickneſſe paſt too and fro in it; but there was no graſſe growing in any ſtreets of note for want of trading as they conceiued; for I per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſwade me as many people paſt too and fro in the ſtreetes of the ſayd City in the higheſt of the ſickneſſe vpon their oc<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>caſions, as did at any time in the ſtreetes of any other City or great Towne of this Kingdome where the ſickneſſe was not, (ſetting Faires and appointed aſſemblies aſide) where<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore we were not all dead. Indeede if God Almighty had goneon in wrath, as of long time you ſee he did continue, we ſhould haue all beene ere long conſumed. But hee is a God of mercy, and is graciouſly pleaſed to leaue ſome be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hind; yea very many for a witneſſe both of his Iuſtice and Mercy.</p>
            <p>And as in my former ſimilitude, after a battell fought aſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>well the ſeuerall armies as the ſeuerall aduerſe Countries, will hearken after and take notice of the loſſe receiued, al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>though they may be much mooued for the ſame: So I per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſwade
<pb n="30" facs="tcp:13094:18"/>my ſelfe both City and Country in this Kingdome that haue had no certainty of the number that haue dyed in this preſent viſitation, although they wiſh well to the City, (it being the harbour of many of their kindred and friends, and in a manner the beauty, wealth and ſtrength of this na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion:) will deſire notwithſtanding to be truly informed; and therefore as ayming altogether, to make my poore ſubiect profitable or pleaſing, or at leaſt wiſe not burthen-ſome to all to whoſe hands it ſhall happen to come, I haue taken this paines to ſet downe the number, both in groſſe and as they dyed weekly, ſo may you perceiue the increaſe and decreaſe.</p>
            <p>
               <table>
                  <head>There dyed in London and the Lyberties thereof.</head>
                  <row>
                     <cell> </cell>
                     <cell>
                        <hi>Totall.</hi>
                     </cell>
                     <cell>
                        <hi>Plague.</hi>
                     </cell>
                  </row>
                  <row>
                     <cell>FRom the 23 of <hi>December</hi> to the 30 of the ſame</cell>
                     <cell>211</cell>
                     <cell>0</cell>
                  </row>
                  <row>
                     <cell>From the 30 of <hi>December</hi> to the 6 of <hi>Ianuary</hi>
                     </cell>
                     <cell>220</cell>
                     <cell>1</cell>
                  </row>
                  <row>
                     <cell>From the 6 of <hi>Ianuary</hi> to the 13. of the ſame</cell>
                     <cell>196</cell>
                     <cell>1</cell>
                  </row>
                  <row>
                     <cell>From the 13 of <hi>Ianuary</hi> to the 20 of the ſame</cell>
                     <cell>240</cell>
                     <cell>0</cell>
                  </row>
                  <row>
                     <cell>From the 20 to the 27</cell>
                     <cell>226</cell>
                     <cell>0</cell>
                  </row>
                  <row>
                     <cell>From the 27 to the 3 of <hi>February</hi>
                     </cell>
                     <cell>174</cell>
                     <cell>3</cell>
                  </row>
                  <row>
                     <cell>From the 3 to the 10</cell>
                     <cell>204</cell>
                     <cell>5</cell>
                  </row>
                  <row>
                     <cell>From the 10 to the 17</cell>
                     <cell>211</cell>
                     <cell>3</cell>
                  </row>
                  <row>
                     <cell>From the 17 to the 24</cell>
                     <cell>252</cell>
                     <cell>1</cell>
                  </row>
                  <row>
                     <cell>From the 24 to the 3 of <hi>March</hi>
                     </cell>
                     <cell>207</cell>
                     <cell>0</cell>
                  </row>
                  <row>
                     <cell>From the 3 to the 10</cell>
                     <cell>210</cell>
                     <cell>0</cell>
                  </row>
                  <row>
                     <cell>From the 10 to the 17</cell>
                     <cell>261</cell>
                     <cell>4</cell>
                  </row>
                  <row>
                     <cell>From the 17 to the 24</cell>
                     <cell>226</cell>
                     <cell>8</cell>
                  </row>
                  <row>
                     <cell>From the 24 to the 31</cell>
                     <cell>243</cell>
                     <cell>11</cell>
                  </row>
                  <row>
                     <cell>From the 31 to the 7 of <hi>April</hi>
                     </cell>
                     <cell>239</cell>
                     <cell>10</cell>
                  </row>
                  <row>
                     <cell>From the 7 to the 14</cell>
                     <cell>256</cell>
                     <cell>24</cell>
                  </row>
                  <row>
                     <cell>From the 14 to the 21</cell>
                     <cell>230</cell>
                     <cell>25</cell>
                  </row>
                  <row>
                     <cell>From the 21 to the 28</cell>
                     <cell>305</cell>
                     <cell>26</cell>
                  </row>
                  <row>
                     <cell>From the 23 to the 5 of <hi>May</hi>
                     </cell>
                     <cell>292</cell>
                     <cell>30</cell>
                  </row>
                  <row>
                     <cell>From the 5 to the 12</cell>
                     <cell>332</cell>
                     <cell>45</cell>
                  </row>
                  <row>
                     <cell>From the 12 to the 19</cell>
                     <cell>379</cell>
                     <cell>71</cell>
                  </row>
                  <row>
                     <cell>From the 19 to the 26</cell>
                     <cell>401</cell>
                     <cell>78</cell>
                  </row>
                  <row>
                     <cell>From the 26 to the 2 of <hi>Iune</hi>
                     </cell>
                     <cell>395</cell>
                     <cell>69</cell>
                  </row>
                  <row>
                     <cell>From the 2 to the 9</cell>
                     <cell>434</cell>
                     <cell>97</cell>
                  </row>
                  <row>
                     <cell>From the 9 to the 16</cell>
                     <cell>510</cell>
                     <cell>165</cell>
                  </row>
                  <row>
                     <cell>From the 16 to the 23</cell>
                     <cell>640</cell>
                     <cell>239</cell>
                  </row>
                  <row>
                     <cell>From the 23 to the 30</cell>
                     <cell>942</cell>
                     <cell>390</cell>
                  </row>
                  <pb n="31" facs="tcp:13094:18"/>
                  <row>
                     <cell>From the 30 to the 7 of <hi>Iuly</hi>
                     </cell>
                     <cell>1222</cell>
                     <cell>593</cell>
                  </row>
                  <row>
                     <cell>From the 7 to the 14</cell>
                     <cell>1741</cell>
                     <cell>1004</cell>
                  </row>
                  <row>
                     <cell>From the 14 to the 21</cell>
                     <cell>2850</cell>
                     <cell>1819</cell>
                  </row>
                  <row>
                     <cell>From the 21 to the 28</cell>
                     <cell>3583</cell>
                     <cell>2471</cell>
                  </row>
                  <row>
                     <cell>From the 28 to the 4 of <hi>Auguſt</hi>
                     </cell>
                     <cell>4517</cell>
                     <cell>3659</cell>
                  </row>
                  <row>
                     <cell>From the 4 of <hi>Auguſt</hi> to the 11</cell>
                     <cell>4855</cell>
                     <cell>4115</cell>
                  </row>
                  <row>
                     <cell>From the 11 to the 18</cell>
                     <cell>5205</cell>
                     <cell>4463</cell>
                  </row>
                  <row>
                     <cell>From the 18 to the 25</cell>
                     <cell>4841</cell>
                     <cell>4218</cell>
                  </row>
                  <row>
                     <cell>From the 25 to the 1 of <hi>September</hi>
                     </cell>
                     <cell>3897</cell>
                     <cell>3344</cell>
                  </row>
                  <row>
                     <cell>From the 1 of <hi>September</hi> to the 8</cell>
                     <cell>3157</cell>
                     <cell>2550</cell>
                  </row>
                  <row>
                     <cell>From the 8 to the 15</cell>
                     <cell>2148</cell>
                     <cell>1672</cell>
                  </row>
                  <row>
                     <cell>From the 15 to the 22</cell>
                     <cell>1994</cell>
                     <cell>1555</cell>
                  </row>
                  <row>
                     <cell>From the 22 to the 29</cell>
                     <cell>1256</cell>
                     <cell>85<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap>
                     </cell>
                  </row>
                  <row>
                     <cell>From the 29 to the 6 of <hi>October</hi>
                     </cell>
                     <cell>838</cell>
                     <cell>538</cell>
                  </row>
                  <row>
                     <cell>From the 6 of <hi>October</hi> to the 13</cell>
                     <cell>
                        <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap>15</cell>
                     <cell>511</cell>
                  </row>
                  <row>
                     <cell>From the 13 to the 20</cell>
                     <cell>651</cell>
                     <cell>331</cell>
                  </row>
                  <row>
                     <cell>From the 20 to the 27</cell>
                     <cell>375</cell>
                     <cell>134</cell>
                  </row>
                  <row>
                     <cell>From the 27 to the 3 of <hi>Nouember</hi>
                     </cell>
                     <cell>357</cell>
                     <cell>89</cell>
                  </row>
                  <row>
                     <cell>From the 3 of <hi>Nouember</hi> to the 10</cell>
                     <cell>319</cell>
                     <cell>92</cell>
                  </row>
                  <row>
                     <cell>From the 10 to the 17</cell>
                     <cell>274</cell>
                     <cell>48</cell>
                  </row>
                  <row>
                     <cell>From the 17 to the 24</cell>
                     <cell>231</cell>
                     <cell>27</cell>
                  </row>
                  <row>
                     <cell>From the 24 to the 1 of <hi>December</hi>
                     </cell>
                     <cell>190</cell>
                     <cell>15</cell>
                  </row>
                  <row>
                     <cell>From the 1 of <hi>December</hi> to the 8</cell>
                     <cell>181</cell>
                     <cell>15</cell>
                  </row>
                  <row>
                     <cell>From the 8 to the 15 of the ſame</cell>
                     <cell>168</cell>
                     <cell>6</cell>
                  </row>
                  <row>
                     <cell cols="2">Totall from the 33 of <hi>December</hi> 1624 to the 15 of <hi>Decem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ber</hi> 1625. 53914. Whereof of the plague. 35417.</cell>
                  </row>
               </table>
            </p>
            <p>The Totall of the laſt great ſickneſſe hapning in the begin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning of the Raigne of our late Soueraigne Lord King <hi>Iames</hi> deceaſed, <hi>viz.</hi> From the 23. of <hi>December</hi> 1602. to the 22. of <hi>December</hi> 1603. there dyed of all diſeaſes in <hi>London</hi> and the Liberties 38244. wherof of the plague 30578. Wherein the greateſt number that dyed in one weeke was in <hi>London</hi> and the Liberties, in all 3385. Whereof the plague, 3035.</p>
            <p>IN Former times this Kingdome and City haue bin like<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wiſe viſited, as ſoone after the Conqueſt of King <hi>William</hi> Duke of <hi>Normandy</hi> there happened a fearefull plague: As likewiſe in the Raigne of King <hi>Edward</hi> the third; and in the yeare 1562. in which yeare there died of the Peſtilence, 20136. alſo in <hi>Anno</hi> 1592. in which yeare there dyed in all 25886. whereof the plague in and about <hi>London,</hi> 1503.</p>
            <p>
               <pb n="32" facs="tcp:13094:19"/>Other parts of the world haue likewiſe felt Gods hand, as you may read in Scripture of <hi>Ieruſalem, &amp;c.</hi> Further it is recorded of the City called the grand <hi>Cair</hi> in <hi>Turkey,</hi> once euery ſeauen yeares there hapneth a vehement Contation, to the loſſe of moſt part of the people there. In <hi>Rome</hi> there haue dyed 2000. a day, and 100000. in a yeare: In <hi>Conſtan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tinople</hi> 5000. a day, and 700000. within ſix months: In the Citty of <hi>Paris</hi> in <hi>France</hi> 100000. in a yeare, <hi>viz.</hi> in <hi>Anno</hi> 1348.</p>
            <p>In <hi>Millan, Padua</hi> and <hi>Venice</hi> 100000. in each City with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>in two yeares: In <hi>Bohemia</hi> 300000. in the like ſpace: and ſo likewiſe in other Cities and Kingdomes, and at ſeuerall times hath God ſhewen his power.</p>
            <lg>
               <l>AS one a ſleepe of many pleaſing toyes</l>
               <l>Oft times doth dreame, and thinkes that he enioyes,</l>
               <l>That which indeed he doth not, when he wakes,</l>
               <l>Into his former dumpes himſelfe betakes;</l>
               <l>So after we ſuch bitter ſtormes had taſted,</l>
               <l>For want of Trade whilſt that the ſickneſſe laſted,</l>
               <l>Luld with vaine hope, when as we ſtill did ſee</l>
               <l>The ſickneſſe ceaſe, that here a Terme ſhould be</l>
               <l>VVithout all queſtion kept: thus thought we then,</l>
               <l>And for a while we were right ioyfull men,</l>
               <l>Our ſhops begin to open we prepare,</l>
               <l>And ſet them out with ſundry ſorts of ware,</l>
               <l>Although before this time windowes ſtood bare,</l>
               <l>Open or ſhut we did not greatly care.</l>
               <l>When newes doth come that ſets vs into paſſion,</l>
               <l>The King proclaimeth by his Proclamation,</l>
               <l>That there no Terme of <hi>Michael</hi> ſhould be kept,</l>
               <l>But where the Proclamation did direct.</l>
               <l>
                  <pb n="24" facs="tcp:13094:19"/>VVhich was to <hi>Reading,</hi> good for <hi>Barke</hi> ſhire men,</l>
               <l>You may coniecture what a plunge we then</l>
               <l>VVere put vnto; how ſhall our Rent be payd,</l>
               <l>And other needments which we want defrayd:</l>
               <l>Now many a poore ſoule in the ſtreetes we ſee,</l>
               <l>For want to beg and craue, which would not be,</l>
               <l>But that the times ſo hard are, others ſham'd,</l>
               <l>(Although their need is great) yet to be nam'd</l>
               <l>A cra<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ing begger, much they would endure</l>
               <l>Ere they could brooke to put the ſame in vre;</l>
               <l>And therefore farre more harder was their caſe,</l>
               <l>Then thoſe that beg'd and car'd not to be baſe:</l>
               <l>Tis ſuch a time that many a ſigh is fet</l>
               <l>By thoſe we good-men call, yet runne in debt,</l>
               <l>And further alſo I thinke like to runne,</l>
               <l>Good Lord amend it elſe we are vndone:</l>
               <l>Albeit 'tis a comfort that we finde</l>
               <l>That King and great men were ſo well inclin'd,</l>
               <l>Their charitable deedes for to expreſſe,</l>
               <l>In theſe our great afflictions to redreſſe</l>
               <l>The wants of poore men which did ſo abound</l>
               <l>VVithin this City that no place was found</l>
               <l>VVithout a multitude, and to preuent,</l>
               <l>Meanes was collected, orders there were ſent</l>
               <l>By Proclamation, how it ſhould be vſde,</l>
               <l>That ſo their worthy deedes be not abuſde:</l>
               <l>This was commended to the weighty care</l>
               <l>Of <hi>Londons</hi> Gouernour the worthy Maior;</l>
               <l>Who in the ſame did ſhew himſelfe vpright,</l>
               <l>Got great applauſe in all the peoples ſight,</l>
               <l>This worthy Act did many others mooue,</l>
               <l>To ſhew their Charity and Chriſtian loue,</l>
               <l>
                  <pb n="34" facs="tcp:13094:20"/>Yea thoſe that had not much themſelues would giue</l>
               <l>Of that they had, poore people to relieue</l>
               <l>In theſe ſad times, abroad and at the doore,</l>
               <l>Thus were we moou'd, ſo far'd it with the poore:</l>
               <l>Examples ſurely are of wondrous force,</l>
               <l>In ſuch ſad times as theſe to ſtrike remorſe</l>
               <l>Into mens hearts, but more when as we ſee</l>
               <l>Before our eyes the woefull miſery</l>
               <l>Of thoſe that want, no doubt moſt that were here</l>
               <l>And ſaw theſe things more liberall farre they were</l>
               <l>Then earſt before, and to tell plaine my minde,</l>
               <l>What others write my ſelfe did daily finde</l>
               <l>Them very free, for whereſoere I was</l>
               <l>At home or broad, giuing there alwayes was</l>
               <l>By one or other, vnto thoſe that cri'd,</l>
               <l>Who hardly of an Almes deed were deni'd</l>
               <l>Of them they askt; foretimes it was not ſo,</l>
               <l>But many ſhould be ask't that would ſay no,</l>
               <l>Before that we would ſee ones wants relieued,</l>
               <l>So hard our hearts were to poore ſoules y'grieued;</l>
               <l>And now to you that in the Country be,</l>
               <l>Heare not the cryes of poore, nor yet doe ſee</l>
               <l>Their miſerable wants, how they haue far'd,</l>
               <l>And how we to our powers haue not ſpar'd</l>
               <l>Our meanes for to relieue them, if we ſlacke,</l>
               <l>Let not our ſlackneſſe you hard hearted make</l>
               <l>When you ſhalberequired, I may ſay,</l>
               <l>We haue done well, whilſt you haue beene away:</l>
               <l>Still neede there is, and like is ſo to be,</l>
               <l>'Twill be a pleaſing thing for vs to ſee</l>
               <l>You home againe in peace, if much you make</l>
               <l>Of poore afflicted ones for Chriſt his ſake.</l>
               <l>
                  <pb n="35" facs="tcp:13094:20"/>LAſtly to all Reſiders of this Land,</l>
               <l>That at this time haue felt the Almighties hand,</l>
               <l>Or ſeene the heauy iudgements that haue beene,</l>
               <l>Sith that the cauſe thereof is onely ſinne,</l>
               <l>For which we haue euduted many a ſmart,</l>
               <l>And oft times gone to bed with aking heart;</l>
               <l>Like dreaded children let vs now be wiſe,</l>
               <l>And haue a care that we doe not deſpiſe,</l>
               <l>Or ſet at light the anger of our God,</l>
               <l>Leaſt he in furie with a greater rod</l>
               <l>In vengeance come vpon vs, warning take</l>
               <l>By this moſt grieuous chaſtment, now awake</l>
               <l>And looke about vs, let vs call to minde</l>
               <l>VVhat mightie Cities we in writings finde,</l>
               <l>That heretofore for glorie bare the bell,</l>
               <l>And through the world did far and neere excell,</l>
               <l>The Famous <hi>Niniue, Ieruſalem,</hi>
               </l>
               <l>
                  <hi>Troy, Carthage, Roome</hi> and many more with them,</l>
               <l>Which for their ſinnes were wholly ouerthrowne,</l>
               <l>Their ſtanding places hardly to be knowne,</l>
               <l>And in this ſad diſaſter let vs not</l>
               <l>Forget the woefull ſtate, which now God wot</l>
               <l>Renown'd <hi>Iudea</hi> and the Eaſterne Lands,</l>
               <l>That now lye groaning vnder Turkiſh bands:</l>
               <l>The famous <hi>Grecia,</hi> many Countries more,</l>
               <l>VVho all one God and Sauiour did adore</l>
               <l>That we do now, but going farre aſtray,</l>
               <l>Haue wrought vnto themſelues ſuch ſad anoy,</l>
               <l>That griefe it is to tell: Oh that my pen,</l>
               <l>Or all the arte I haue could now mooue men,</l>
               <l>To leaue their euill courſes, and to turne</l>
               <l>Vnto their maker, inwardly to mourne</l>
               <l>
                  <pb n="36" facs="tcp:13094:21"/>For what hath bin the cauſe of this ſad woe,</l>
               <l>And gaine the loue of him that now our foe.</l>
               <l>Appeares to be: how haue we wandred wide,</l>
               <l>In vaine exceſſe of ryot, ſinfull pride,</l>
               <l>Where was the loue that with vs ſhould be found,</l>
               <l>And with Gods ſeruants ſhould to all abound,</l>
               <l>VVas it not turn'd to hatred and deſpite,</l>
               <l>Or ſuch a loue as ſtrayd farre from the right,</l>
               <l>Moſt filthy fraud, we lou'd for to deceiue,</l>
               <l>And if we could our neighbours to bereaue</l>
               <l>Of that they had, be't but a good name,</l>
               <l>(If we had none) we enui'd at the ſame,</l>
               <l>Our ſwearing and blaſpheming, hatefull lyes,</l>
               <l>Haue pe'rſt the very Heauens and there cries</l>
               <l>For flaming vengeance, and our great oppreſſion</l>
               <l>Haue there bin likewiſe, and haue made confeſſion</l>
               <l>Before we'd do't our ſelues, our beaſtly luſt</l>
               <l>And many other ſinnes did ſticke as ruſt</l>
               <l>Vpon our ſinfull ſoules, oh now like men</l>
               <l>Lets rouſe theſe dang'rous Adders from their den,</l>
               <l>Theſe haue bin they that haue our ſorrows ſought,</l>
               <l>And theſe were they that to deſtruction brought</l>
               <l>The other wofull Countries: theſe are they</l>
               <l>That if we not forſake them will deſtroy</l>
               <l>Our wofull Land likewiſe, now let vs weepe</l>
               <l>And drench our eyes in flouds of ſorrowes deepe,</l>
               <l>That we ſo great a God haue not regarded,</l>
               <l>Conclude that we moſt iuſtly are rewarded</l>
               <l>For our miſdeedes, and let vs from them ceaſe,</l>
               <l>This is the way to make a finall peace</l>
               <l>'Twixt God and vs; ſo let all good men pray</l>
               <l>Amen, Amen with me, God grant we may.</l>
            </lg>
            <trailer>FINIS.</trailer>
            <pb facs="tcp:13094:21"/>
         </div>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>
